Guide to the Benjamin Pogrund Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Subject Files, 1939-1995, undated
  - South African Coloured National Convention
    - Proposal, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 77)
    - Reports, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 78)
  - South African Communist Party, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 79)
  - South African Council on Trade Unions, 1963 (Box 16, Folder 80)
  - South African Information Service, 1986-1988, undated (Box 16, Folder 81)
  - South African Institute of International Affairs, 1948, undated (Box 16, Folder 82)
  - South African Institute of Personnel Management, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 83)
  - South African Institute of Race Relations
    - General, 1958-1981, undated (Box 16, Folder 84-85)
    - Penal reform, 1941-1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 86)
    - Reports, 1955-1960 (Box 16, Folder 87)
  - South African Press
    - General, 1987-1988, undated (Box 16, Folder 88)
    - Media regulations [compiled by Bell, Dewar, and Hall, attorneys], 1987-1988 (Box 16, Folder 89-90)
    - Namibia and the Media Conference, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 91)
    - Newspaper bill, 1977, undated (Box 17, Folder 92)
    - Speeches and papers, 1983-1984, undated (Box 17, Folder 93)
  - South African Press Council, 1977, undated (Box 17, Folder 94)
  - South African Society of Journalists, 1967-1981 (Box 17, Folder 95-96)
  - Soweto Uprising [tenth anniversary], 1986 (Box 17, Folder 97)
  - Teacher's Educational and Professional Association [re: coloured education], 1961 (Box 17, Folder 98)
  - Technology, 1986-1991 (Box 17, Folder 99)
  - Tuberculosis among the South African Bantu, 1944 (Box 17, Folder 100)
  - Union Council of Coloured Affairs, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 101)
  - University of Witwatersrand
    - African Studies Institute, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 102)
    - Rand Bursary Fund, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 103)
  - Wentzel, Rosemary
    - General, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 104)
    - Clippings, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 105)
  - Women's League for Racial Harmony, ca. 1962 (Box 17, Folder 106)
  - World Press Freedom Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 17, Folder 107)
- Writings, 1957-1994
  The series is organized alphabetically within four sections: books, magazine articles, newspaper articles, and speeches. The writings cover almost four decades of Pogrund's work, but should not be considered comprehensive.
  The books section includes documentation on two monographs. The files for the unpublished "Communist Activity in South Africa from 1945" contain extensive notes Pogrund prepared for a major study on the South African Communist Party that political and personal circumstances prevented him from actually writing. Organized by chapter, the files include notes from interviews and other sources. Researchers should consult the first folder "Hypotheses and outline" to obtain detailed information on Pogrund's plan for the layout and arguments of the book. The files for How Can Man Die Better include correspondence and research materials used by Pogrund in writing the book. A small amount of correspondence with Veronica Sobukwe can be found in these files, but the bulk of Pogrund's and Robert Sobukwe's correspondence with her can be found in Series I.
  Pieces mostly on apartheid, prison conditions, and other South African affairs that Pogrund wrote for major magazines such as the Economist, the New Republic, and the Nation comprise the small Journal articles section.
  Newspaper articles document Pogrund's extensive writing for several papers in South Africa, England, and the United States, but predominantly for the Boston Globe and the Rand Daily Mail. Most of the writings are clippings and are sorted only by year. Separate folders documenting his work in 1960-1961 as African affairs reporter and his 1982 trip to Israel are listed with other chronologically arranged Rand Daily Mail materials.
  Seven folders of speeches, most of which address South African affairs and journalism, are arranged chronologically. An address to the United Nations Special Committee Against Apartheid on the occasion of the tenth anniversary of the death of Robert Sobukwe highlights the section.
  - Books
    - Communist Activity in South Africa from 1945 [unpublished], [1964-1966]
      - Hypotheses and outline (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Chapter 1. "Communism" in South Africa (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Chapter 2. History of the Communist Party in South Africa (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Chapter 3. The Communist Party of South Africa in 1945 (Box 18, Folder 4-8)
      - Chapter 4. Post-war period: 1945 to 1948 (Box 18, Folder 9-13)
      - Chapter 4. Post-war period: 1945 to 1948 (Box 19, Folder 14-21)
      - Chapter 5. 1948: Nationalist government elected (Box 19, Folder 22-23)
      - Chapter 6. 1948 to 1950: The banning of the Communist Party (Box 20, Folder 24-32)
      - Chapter 7. ANC Youth League and the growth of Communist influence (Box 20, Folder 33-35)
      - Chapter 7. ANC Youth League and the growth of Communist influence (Box 21, Folder 36-41)
      - Chapter 8. Communist influence grows and expands in new directions (Box 21, Folder 42-45)
      - Chapter 8. Communist influence grows and expands in new directions (Box 22, Folder 46-49)
      - Chapter 9. Communist influence spreads: Congress of Democrats (Box 22, Folder 50-53)
      - Chapter 10. Communist influence spreads: South African Coloured People's Organization (Box 23, Folder 54-56)
      - Chapter 11. Communist influence spreads: South African Congress of Trade Unions (Box 23, Folder 57)
      - Chapter 13. Communist influence spreads: other organizations (Box 23, Folder 58-60)
      - Chapter 14. The press (Box 23, Folder 61)
      - Chapter 15. Congress of the People (Box 23, Folder 62-63)
      - Chapter 16. Communist international links (Box 24, Folder 64)
      - Chapter 17. 1955 to 1960 (Box 24, Folder 65-67)
      - Chapter 18. 1960: Anti-pass campaign and state of emergency (Box 24, Folder 68-70)
      - Chapter 19. Anti-Republic Campaign and call for a National Convention (Box 24, Folder 71-72)
      - Chapter 19. Anti-Republic Campaign and call for a National Convention (Box 25, Folder 73-74)
      - Chapter 20. Postscript: 1961 to 1963 (Box 25, Folder 75-76)
      - Notes from multiple chapters (Box 25, Folder 77)
    - How Can Man Die Better: The Life of Robert Sobukwe
      - Correspondence, 1980-1990 (Box 25, Folder 78)
        Series I, folders 49-51
      - Research and publication materials, 1957, 1978-1990 (Box 25, Folder 79)
  - Magazine articles
    - The Economist, 1974-1985 (Box 26, Folder 80-81)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1994 (Box 26, Folder 82)
  - Newspapers
    - Boston Globe
      - 1976-1978 (Box 26, Folder 83-88)
        Oversize, folder 1
      - 1979-1980 (Box 27, Folder 89-98)
      - 1981-1983 (Box 28, Folder 99-105)
      - 1983-1985 (Box 29, Folder 106-117)
    - Politiken [Copenhagen], 1985 (Box 30, Folder 118)
    - Rand Daily Mail [Johannesburg]
      - General articles, 1958-1984 (Box 30, Folder 119-124)
        Oversize, folder 2
      - African affairs reports, 1960-1961 (Box 30, Folder 125-129)
      - Prison conditions
        Series II, folders 29-32
      - Reports on trip to Israel, 1982 (Box 30, Folder 130)
        Series V, folders 5-6
        Series V, folder 4
    - Sunday Times [London], 1964-1972 (Box 31, Folder 131-132)
    - Today [London], 1986 (Box 31, Folder 133-135)
    - The World [Johannesburg], 1959-1960 (Box 31, Folder 136-137)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1985 (Box 32, Folder 138-139)
  - Speeches
    - General, 1969-1993, undated (Box 32, Folder 140-146)
    - Tenth Anniversary of the death of Robert Sobukwe, Special Committee Against Apartheid, United Nations, 1988 (Box 32, Folder 147)
- Photographs, 1961-1994
  Arranged alphabetically, Photographs depict Pogrund in a number of different settings, including the Rand Daily Mail "Prisons Case," a trip to Israel, and at the launch of the Daily Mail, a South African newspaper modeled on the Rand Daily Mail. The series also holds photographs of Stephen Biko, Josias Madzunya, Laurence Gandar, Kelsey Stuart, John Scholes, Robert Sobukwe, and Filisberto Taimo.
  - Biko, Stephen, undated (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Daily Mail [launch of Johannesburg newspaper], 1991 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Gregory, James [Nelson Mandela's prison guard], 1994 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Israel, trip to
    - Photographs of Pogrund, 1982 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1982 (Box 33, Folder 5-6)
  - Madzunya, Josias, 1983 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Pogrund, Benjamin [leaving Johannesburg Magistrate's Court after discharge], 1961 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Rand Daily Mail "Prisons Case"
    - Pogrund, Benjamin, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Pogrund, Benjamin and Laurence Gandar, 1968-1969 (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Stuart, Kelsey [attorney for Rand Daily Mail ], ca. 1968 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous individuals, 1968-1969 (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - Sacks, Andrew, undated (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Scholes, John, undated (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - Sobukwe, Robert, 1964, undated (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - Taimo, Filisberto, [1965] (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - Theron, Johannes Adries, undated (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - Sketches, undated (Box 33, Folder 19)
- Oversize, 1961-1994
  - Scrapbooks
    - Boston Globe [clippings of Pogrund's writings], 1976-1977 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Rand Daily Mail
      - Clippings of Pogrund's writings, 1959-1961 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - "Prisons Case"
        - 1965-1969 (Box 35, Folder 3-4)
        - 1965-1969 (Box 36, Folder 5)
        - 1966-1969 (Box 37, Folder 6)
        - Gandar, Laurence, 1965-1985 (Box 37, Folder 7)
      - Wine Festival, 1978 (Box 37, Folder 8)